A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 2010-2013
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 2010-2013
The Library of Virginia
51123
11.2 cubic feet (32 Boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Administration
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted documents have been sealed within the collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Secretary of Administration on January 8, 2014.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
The Secretary of Administration is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, is appointed by the governor, and is subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary of Administration oversees general government operations to ensure efficient and effective management of government resources. During Governor Tim Robert McDonnell's term, the Secretary of Administration was responsible for the direction of, or had jurisdiction over, 8 state agencies and boards as follows: Compensation Board, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Department of Minority Business Enterprises, and the State Board of Elections. These agencies mangage the state's real estate portfolio, serve as the state building official, administer employee policies and benefits, oversee procurement, provide laboratory services, promote business opportunities for Small, Women and Minority owned businesses, supervise elections, direct state funds to constitutional officers and public broadcasing entities and safeguard human rights, just to name a few of the important functions handled by agencies under the Secretary of Administration.
Governor Robert McDonnell appointed Lisa Hicks-Thomas to serve as Secretary of Administration in 2010. Mrs. Hicks-Thomas graduated from the University of Virginia in Charlottesville, receiving a Bachelor of Arts Degree in History in 1991, and went on to attend the Marshall-Wythe School of Law at the College of William and Mary where she received her Juris Doctorate in 1994. She began her career as a prosecuting attorney in the Chesapeake Commonwealth’s Attorney’s Office and in 2001 joined the Virginia Attorney General's Office as an Assistant Attorney General and Chief of the newly-formed Computer Crimes Unit. In 2007, Attorney General Bob McDonnell appointed Lisa Hicks-Thomas as his Deputy Attorney General managing a staff of attorneys and overseeing the legal work for the Transportation, Real Estate, Environmental and Technology Division of the Office of the Attorney General. Lisa Hicks-Thomas, a native of Chesapeake, Va., is married to Samuel Thomas and has two children.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Administration records consist of 32 archival boxes and are divided into 7 series. Series have been designated for Correspondence and supporting documentation: Assigned State Agencies; Correspondence and supporting documentation: Constitutent Correspondence; Correspondence and supporting documentation: Office of the Secretary; Environmental Impact Statements; Legislative Files; Real Property and Capital Outlay; Special Projects. These records document the work of the Secretary of Administration during the McDonnell administration and were created or collected, 2010-2013, though some documents in this collection pre-date this time period.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2010-2013
Series II. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Constituent Correspondence, 2010-2013
Series III. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Office of the Secretary, 2010-2013
Series IV. Environmental Impact Statements, 2010-2013
Series V. Legislative Files, 2010-2013
Series VI. Real Property and Capital Outlay, 2010-2013
Series VII. Special Projects, 2010-2013.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2010-2013., Extent: 8 boxes. (Box 1-8)
  This series is housed in 8 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by agency. These files include correspondence, along with subject files and supporting materials such as briefs, meeting records, presentations, and reports. Several state agencies operated under the Office of the Secretary of Administration and were referred to as assigned agencies. The assigned agencies of the Office of the Secretary of Administration documented here include the Compensation Board, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Dept. of Minority Business Enterprise, and the State Board of Elections.
  - Compensation Board: Agency overview information, 2010. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Compensation Board: Budget, 2012-2013. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Compensation Board: Circuit Court Clerks, 2010. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Compensation Board: Commonwealth's Attorneys, 2012 Mar-Dc. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Compensation Board: Commonwealth's Attorneys, 2012 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Compensation Board: Commonwealth's Attorneys, 2013. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Compensation Board: Correspondence (General), 2010-2011. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Compensation Board: Examining Constitutional Officers (Reports), 2010. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Compensation Board: Fines and Fees Report (FY2010) - Exposure draft, 2010. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Compensation Board: Fines and Fees Report (FY2010) - Final, 2010. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Compensation Board: Fines and Fees Report (FY2012), 2012. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Compensation Board: Jail Cost Report (FY2009), 2010. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Compensation Board: Jail Cost Report (FY2010), 2011. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Compensation Board: Jail Cost Report (FY2011), 2012. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Compensation Board: Jail Cost Report (FY2012), 2013. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Compensation Board: Mental Illness in Jails Reports, 2010-2011; 2013. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Compensation Board: Reports of Financial Conditions, 2010-2013. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Employee Dispute Resolution, Dept. of: Correspondence, 2010-2012. (Box 2, Folder 8a)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Alternative Fuel Fleet, 2010-2013. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Building rental rates, 2011. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Captitol Square protests, 2012. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Capitol Square regulations, 2012. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Consolidated Laboratory Services - Newborn screening, 2013. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Correspondence (General), 2010. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Correspondence (General), 2011-2013. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Design Build and Construction Management Procedures, 2012. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General Services, Dept. of: ESCO Contractors Pool, 2012. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Fort Monroe, 2010. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Introduction to DGS, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Labor and Industry, Dept. of - Move, 2010. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Mansion, 2010-2011. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - General Services, Dept. of: State owned vehicles - Progress reports, 2008-2010. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Surplus property, 2010. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Surplus property, 2011. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Surplus property, 2012. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Surplus property, 2013. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Virginia Port Authority - Lease, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Virginia Port Authority - Lease, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General Services, Dept. of: Virginia Port Authority - Lease, 2010. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Consumer-Driven Health Plan (Wellness Engine), 2012. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Correspondence (General), 2010. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Correspondence (General), 2011-2013. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: COVA Connect Health Care Pilot, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Employee Engagement, 2010. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Governor's Public Service Awards, 2012. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Governor's Public Service Awards and Governor's 30 Day Sprint, 2012-2013. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Health insurance premiums, 2010-2012. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Healthcare, 2011-2012. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Payroll premium tax (Workers' Compensation Commission), 2010 Sept. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Report of Workers' Compensation Program Settlements and Experience-Based Premium Recommendations, 2011. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: Report of Workers' Compensation Program Settlements and Experience-Based Premium Recommendations, 2013. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: State application conviction question, 2012. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: State Employee Compensation Review Workgroup, 2013. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: State Employees, 2011-2013. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: State Employees (Binder, Part I), 2012. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: State Employees (Binder, Part II), 2012. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Human Resource Management, Dept. of: State Employees (Binder, Part III), 2012. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Human Rights Council: Correspondence, 2012. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of: Correspondence, 2010. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of: Correspondence, 2011. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of: Correspondence, 2012. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of: Merger of DMBE and Dept. of Business Assistance (Consolidation), 2013. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of: Supplier Diversity / SWaM, 2010. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Minority Business Enterprise, Dept. of: VDOT meeting, 2012. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Elections: Certification of Election for U.S. Senate (Tim Kaine), 2012. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - State Board of Elections: Correspondence, 2010-2013. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - State Board of Elections, Dept. of: Election, 2012. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - State Board of Elections: Electoral College, 2012. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - State Board of Elections: Meeting, 2010 Sept. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - State Board of Elections: Meeting, 2013 Oct. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - State Board of Elections: Reports on audit, 2007-2008. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - State Board of Elections, Dept. of: Staffing, 2010-2011. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Series II. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Constituent correspondence, 2010-2013., Extent: 1 box. (Box 9)
  Constituent Correspondence, 2010-2014, is housed in 1 archival box and is arranged alphabetically by correspondent surname. This series documents correspondence received by the Secretary of Administration during Governor McDonnell's administration. This series contains constituent correspondence pertaining to the agencies overseen by the Office of the Secretary of Administration. This series includes correspondence that was originally addressed to Governor Kaine and then referred to the Secretary of Administration for response on behalf of the Governor, as well as letters addressed directly to the Secretary. Includes incoming correspondence from the general public, as well as from businessmen and civic leaders, college and university officials, and state and federal government officials and legislators, including correspondence from members of the Virginia General Assembly. Also includes some copies of outgoing responses. Some constituent concerns include bonuses for state employees, health insurance coverage, proposed electronic signage for the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, supplier diversity, and procurement and voting issues, amonth others.
  - Constituent correspondence (A), 2010-2013. (Box 9)
  - Constituent correspondence (B), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Constituent correspondence (C), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Constituent correspondence (D), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Constituent correspondence (E-G), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Constituent correspondence (H), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Constituent correspondence (J-L), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Constituent correspondence (M-O), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Constituent correspondence (P-R), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Constituent correspondence (S), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Constituent correspondence (T-V), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Constituent correspondence (W), 2010-2013. (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series III. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Office of the Secretary, 2010-2013., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 10-11)
  Correspondence and supporting documentation: Office of the Secretary, 2010-2013, is house in 2 boxes and is arranged alphabetically. This series includes includes incoming and outgoing correspondece, as well as subject files. Types of documentation include correspondence, articles, briefs, meeting records, notes, and reports. The subject files accumulated by the Secretary document budgeting and financial statements, cabinet meetings and retreats, decision briefs, and other matters with which the Secretary was involved.
  - Administration press briefing, 2011. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Audit reports, 2009-2013. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Agency head meetings, 2010-2013. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Budget Plan (2012-2014 Biennium), 2011. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Budget savings, 2013. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Cabinet meetings, 2010-2013. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Cabinet Retreat, 2010 Sept. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Cabinet Retreat, 2011 Oct. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Cabinet Retreat, 2012 Sept. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Cooperative contacts and alliances, 2010-2013. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2010. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 2011-2013. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Decision briefs, 2010-2013. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Decision tracking sheets, 2010. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Decision tracking sheets, 2011. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Decision tracking sheets, 2012. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Financial statements, 2010-2011. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Financial statements, 2012. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Financial statements, 2013. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Government Reform Commission, 2010-2011. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Interagency Economic Development Working Group, 2010. (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Series IV. Environmental impact reports, 2010-2013., Extent: 7 boxes. (Box 12-18)
  This series is housed in 7 boxes and is arranged chronologically by date of approval or disapproval of the memo. This series contains environmental impact reports and studies created by state agencies prior to beginning construction projects. Section 10.1-1188 et seq., of the Code of Virginia requires that any state agency, institution or branch of government proposing to undertake a "major state project" prepare an environmental impact report. A "major state project" is defined as construction of a facility costing $100,000 or more, or the acquisition of land for which construction is contemplated. The Governor's approval of the report is required before any funds are expended.
  The report packets include the memorandum of approval (or approval with stipulations or disapproval); comments by the Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ) that include a description of the project, environmental impacts and mitigation, and regulatory and coordination needs; and various other memos and correspondence. The DEQ comments take into consideration the impact on water quality and wetlands, erosion and sediment control and stormwater management, air quality, solid waste and hazardous waste management, natural heritage resources, wildlife resources, historic and archaeological resources, forestry and tree protection, geologic and mineral resources, energy conservation, transportation, the Chesapeake Bay Preservation Act, and local and regional concerns. Other agencies such as local governments, regional planning district commissions, the Department of Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of Historic Resources, Department of Transportation, Department of Game and Inland Fisheries and the Virginia Marine Resources Commission were also consulted and asked to comment on any potential problems.
  The projects range from small renovations and additions, to large scale construction efforts. The majority of the projects took place on university or community college campuses, but also includes projects of state agencies including Western State Hospital, Dept. of Corrections, Dept. of Game and Inland Fisheries, and the Dept. of State Police, among others.
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Jan. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Feb. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Mar. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Apr. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 May. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 June. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 July 1-26. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 July 26-29. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Aug. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Sept. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Oct. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Nov. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2010 Dec. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Jan. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Feb. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Mar. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Apr. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 May 9. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 May 26-31. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 June 9-15. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 June 28-29. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 July. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Aug. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Oct. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Nov. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2011 Dec. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Jan. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Feb. (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Mar 9-13. (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Mar 23-29. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Apr. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 May 3-17. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 May 17-31. (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 June. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 July. (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Aug. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Sept. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2012 Nov-Dec. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Jan. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Feb. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Mar. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Apr. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 May 7-10. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 May 13-21. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 June. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 July. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Aug. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Sept. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Oct. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Nov. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Environmental impact reports, 2013 Dec. (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Series V. Legislative files, 2010-2012., Extent: 1 box. (Box 18)
  Legislative files, 2010-2012, are housed in 1 box and are arranged chronologically. These legislative files document General Assembly activity involving the agencies assigned to the Secretary of Administraion and include input from agency heads as to how legislation might effect agency operations. This series includes copies of legislation, correspondence, memoranda and notes. A 2012 binder includes all legislation introduced by agencies assigned to the Secretary of Administration. The legislation in this series contains information on a variety of subjects, the most prevalent being health care, voting, and transportation finance.
  - Legislative files, 2010. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Legislative files, 2011. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Legislative files, 2012. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - VDOT bonding bill, 2012. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Voter ID bills, 2012. (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Series VI. Real Property, 2010-2013., Extent: 3 boxes. (Box 19-21)
  Real Property files, 2010-2013, are housed in 3 boxes and is arranged alphabetically. This series includes correspondence, deeds, leases, memoranda, recommendation forms and reports that document the disposition, funding, maintenance and operation of certain state builidngs as well as other real property issues handled by the Department of General Services (DGS). The DGS Recommendation forms cover Deeds, Disposition of Surplus Property, Expense Leases, Income Leases, Purchase Agreements, Right of Way, Temporary Transfers, and Utility Easements. Transfers, and include approvals (by the Secretary of Administration, DGS Director, and the Director of the Real Estate Division), as well as background information and intended use of the property.
  - Combined Real Estate Report (DGS), 2010-2011. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Hampton, Virginia School for the Deaf and Blind, 2011-2012. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations, 2010 July-Aug. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations, 2010 Sept-Oct. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations, 2010 Nov-Dec. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Recommendations, 20111 Jan-Feb. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Recommendations, 2011 Mar-Apr. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Recommendations, 2011 May-June. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Recommendations, 2011 July-Aug. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations, 2011 Sept-Oct. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Recommendations, 2011 Nov-Dec. (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Recommendations, 2012 Jan-Feb. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Recommendations, 2012 Mar-Apr. (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations, 2012 May-June. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations, 2012 July-Aug. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations, 2012 Sept-Oct. (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Recommendations, 2012 Nov-Dec. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Recommendations, 2013 Jan-Feb. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Recommendations, 2013 Mar-Apr. (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Recommendations, 2013 May. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations, 2013 June-July. (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Recommendations, 2013 Aug-Sept. (Box 20, Folder 11)